<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Prince of Conde and his associates to the Queene, vppon the iudgement of rebellion, set forth against the[m] by their enemies, terming the[m] selues to be the court of parlamente of Parys, with a protestation of the evils and inconueniences which may thereof ensue..</title>
            <author>Condé, Louis, prince de, 1530-1569.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1562</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94038</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">72799635</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 72799635</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184101</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07937)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184101)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2228:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Prince of Conde and his associates to the Queene, vppon the iudgement of rebellion, set forth against the[m] by their enemies, terming the[m] selues to be the court of parlamente of Parys, with a protestation of the evils and inconueniences which may thereof ensue..</title>
                  <author>Condé, Louis, prince de, 1530-1569.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Paules Churchyarde by Lucas Harryson.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1562..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date taken from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Historiated initial.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁸ D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Condé, Louis, --  prince de, 1530-1569 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:4"/>
            <p>A DECLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Prince of Conde and his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates to the Queene, vppon the Iudgement of rebellion, ſet forth againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their enemies, terming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues to be the Court of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamente of Parys, with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the euils and inconueniences which may thereof enſue.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London in Paules Churchyarde by Lucas Harryſon.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:5"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthoughe that the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngs hereto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore publiſhed in the name of the Prince of Conde, and al the Princes, Lordes, gentlemen and other which are of his company, do ſufficiently declare the equity of the cauſe whiche hath ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them, as well for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the King and conſerua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of hys authoritye, as for the mayntayning of his edic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or proclamatyons, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the holy liberty and quietneſſe of conſcience of the refourmed Churches within this realme: neuertheleſſe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the enemies of the honour of God, and publique
<pb facs="tcp:184101:6"/> quietneſſe, dayly ſet forth new ſclaunders, wherby they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to oppreſſe the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cye of the ſayd Prince and hys aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates, it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth wyth good reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that if the wicked ceaſſe not to aſſayle equitye and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the good alſo ſhould not ceaſſe to defend it.</p>
            <p>Now for bycauſe that the 27. day of Iuly laſt paſt, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was geuen in the Court of parlement of <hi>Parys,</hi> whereby they pretende to declare them rebelles, that haue taken ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour for the ſeruice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King, the conſeruation of the ſtates authority, and to reſiſt the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence and tyranny of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke of Guyſe and his adherentes: it is neceſſary that the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this iudgemente ſhoulde be manifeſted, as wel to thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:184101:6"/> of this kingdome, as to ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: &amp; namely that it ſhould be repreſented to our poſtery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by this declaration. For it ſhal ſerue for an example of remembraunce, wherein may be ſeene, how muche the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God and perſecutors of his Church, are of corrupte vnderſtanding and iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and farre from all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. We may (I ſay) perceue, that men whiche prefer theyr lyes and errors to the ſacred truth of God, are ſo farre blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they iudge thoſe ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, which go about to ſeke (as much as in them lieth) the publique vnion and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: and condemne thoſe for rebels, which forſaking theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, geuing ouer their goods, do hazard their lyues,
<pb facs="tcp:184101:7"/> to the end y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the King may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine obeyed, and the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of hys Edictes may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolably kept.</p>
            <p>And to the end that ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of rebellyon may be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uinced of manifeſt iniuſtice, and be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of an enemy, and not for the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a Iudge: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and hys aſſociats ſhal declare to this effect, following theyr firſt proteſtations and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges concerning the verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their innocency.</p>
            <p>Firſt as concerning the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the perſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Prince, he is ſo much affected to the ſeruice of the King, that he feeleth himſelfe wounded &amp; burthened with that, whiche they lay to other, whome hee
<pb facs="tcp:184101:7"/> knoweth neuer meante anye ſuch thing in takyng armour, nor tended to none other end, but to the conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thys crowne. And the ſayd Prince is ſo farre from beyng pleaſed with thys exception, that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he is offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded: in that they would ſeparate him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good and faythfull ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the King, and from as good and holy a company, as euer was aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled together in this realme. For this cauſe being aſſured both before God and Man, that their innocency is ſuch, that al the lyes and ſcla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſtayne wyth one onlye ſpot of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and rebellion, eyther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Prince or his aſſociates: he deſyreth to haue the ſame conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with them which are
<pb facs="tcp:184101:8"/> ioyned with hym in the ſame goodnes of cauſe, theſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, theſame wil to beſtow their liues for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings welth, conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his eſtate, and the eſtablyſhyng of the pure ſeruyce of God in hys King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>And euen as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Prince cannot, nor oughte not to be forſaken or denied of thoſe at whoſe commaundemente he hath iuſtlye taken weapon in hand: no more woulde he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe which haue (at his requeſt) take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> armes with him, and with whom he hath lyke entent and wil. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, he hath ſufficient expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in the crafty ſleyghtes of hys enemies, to perceaue what they brue vnder ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor and pretence of exception:
<pb facs="tcp:184101:8"/> as it is eaſy to be iudged by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lettres miſſiue, ſente through the prouinces, wherein he is generally compriſed wyth the others. Now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may appeare that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crime of rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to light vpon thoſe, whiche of their own authoritie haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken weapon, to breake the Edicts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng, and to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the quietneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole realme, &amp; not vpon any other, which haue taken armoure to withſtand ſo pernicious an e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trepryſe, we will brieflye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which wee haue am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply diſcourſed in oure former writinges.</p>
            <p>Ech ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knoweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Edict of Ianuary, brought ſuch quy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etneſſe throughout al Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that it ſeemed that the eſtate of thys realme beynge before
<pb facs="tcp:184101:9"/> toſſed with infinyte troubles and tempeſts, was (as it wer) arriued at a happy and quiet porte. At that tyme when the Duke of Guyſe, through the ſlaughter whiche he made at <hi>Vaſſy.</hi> gaue openly to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that he had ſworne war agaynſt the eſtate of the King and the welth and quietneſſe of his people. The which with good right was thought very ſtraunge by the ſayd Prynce, who for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place which he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ought of duety to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerue and mayntayne the authority &amp; hyghneſſe of the King: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayd Guyſe hath alwayes gone aboute to brynge to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme ruine. That (I ſay) was thought marueilous ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, that a ſubiecte durſt ſo many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly breake an Edicte of hys
<pb facs="tcp:184101:9"/> Prynce, yea ſuch an Edict as was made by the delyberatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the eſtates, authoryzed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings Counſel, with the moſt notable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany that could be gathered and choſen out of al the Courts of Parlemente of this realme, And although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Prince, had of hys owne right, occaſion iuſt enough to withſtand ſo manifeſte a vyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and oppreſſion to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King and hys Edictes, yet he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held him ſelf to entrepriſe any thing to this effect vntill he re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaued commaundement.</p>
            <p>In conſideration whereof the ſayd Prince moſt humbly beſecheth the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty to remembre that beyng at <hi>S, Germayne in Laye,</hi> ſhe was aduertiſed to what ende the Duke of Guyſe tended: which
<pb facs="tcp:184101:10"/> was to depoſe hyr fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hyr au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and to banyſh from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout hyr, hir moſt faythfull &amp; louing ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might the eaſlyer obtayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this realme. Whereto they haue alwayes caſte their eye and aſpyred, ſince the time that thei haue had any mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of affayres in their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Which being come to the Queenes knowledge, &amp; lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the faction that by the meanes of the Embaſſadoure of Spayne they practized, in fauor of theyr entrepryſe: ſhee conceiued ſuch grefe therof, as the great and eminent daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger required. Which gaue hir occaſion one euening, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre the ſaid Prince, to gather together the greateſt numbre of Gentlemen that hee could,
<pb facs="tcp:184101:10"/> that the effecte of ſo daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous an enterpriſe myghte be preuented. Which he faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly went about, hauing reſpect to the commaundement of the Queene, and of hys duety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the kynges maieſtie and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hys crown. Now thys obedience was the beginning of all that, whiche hath ſince continued, in reſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe which the Queene iudged to be her enemies, and of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe would take hede. And for greater witneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doubt which ſhe had of them, it may pleaſe her to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the charge whiche ſhe once gaue to the ſayd Prynce, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſecretary <hi>Marſeille.</hi> Now when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Guyſes by theyr demeanours as well at <hi>Parys</hi> as elſwher, had brought
<pb facs="tcp:184101:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:184101:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:184101:12"/> openly to light that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Queene confirmed and repeted again to the ſayd Prynce, as well by letters as meſſangers, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente which ſhe had alredy made, to reſiſt the force &amp; violence whiche they deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to make agaynſte hyr Maieſty. Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this behalfe he moſt humbly beſecheth &amp; ſo farre as the word of a Quene ought to remayne ſure &amp; inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable, to call to minde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which ſhe hath written w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hir own hand: the which he is now conſtrayned to ſet forthe to all mennes eyes, that they may al read hys innocency in the very lettres of the Quene. For he is aſſured that ſhe hath not forgotten that whiche ſhe wrote to him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tainebleau,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:184101:12"/> in the moneth of Marche laſt paſt: recommending vnto hym the conſeruation of the Kings perſon &amp; of hirs, in theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: I reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend vnto you the mother and hyr children. And conſequently that which ſhee wrote w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her hand by <hi>Monſieur de Bouchauannes,</hi> when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force of the Guyſes was in <hi>Parys:</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is that he ſhould not dyſarme himſelfe, vntill his enemies were diſarmed, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it might be ſeene to what end their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy would tend. And here vpon the ſayd Prince deſireth that it wil pleaſe hir Maieſty to remembre, howe often ſhe hath giuen him to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that ſhe eſtemed that whiche he did for verye agreable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice the which ſhee woulde ſo print in the Kings memorie,
<pb facs="tcp:184101:13"/> that (being come to age,) hee might gratefy him according to his deſert.</p>
            <p>Wherunto lykewiſe agreeth that which ſhe ſaid to the lord Admirall, not longe before he departed from the court, that ſhe knewe hym ſo faythfull a ſeruaunt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kinges and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſo louing toward her maie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtie, that if nede required, he would not lette by al meanes poſſible, to endeuor hymſelfe to defend hir from the conſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy of the Guyſes. As ſhe alſo now laſte writte vnto hym by <hi>Monſiur Re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bouillet,</hi> that ſhe eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med hym ſo good a ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Kings, and deſirous of the conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his eſtate, that ſhe would vſe hys counſell for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pacifyi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troubles which were in thoſe dayes. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore
<pb facs="tcp:184101:13"/> the talke whych ſhe had beſides <hi>Baugency</hi> with the ſayd Prince &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords which wer in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, is ſo cleare wytneſſe of hir conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing therof, that it ſhuld be to ſuperfluous to allege infinyte other proues, which myght be broght forth to this effect. For then in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of .7. Knigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the ordre, &amp; certaine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtate, ſhe largly thanked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde Prince &amp; hys company, for the ſeruice and pleaſure that ſhe had receiued of them: vſing theſe termes: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe acknowleged y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Kings life &amp; hirs were conſerued and kept through their meane.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as behoueth, what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may remayne to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes of the ſayde Prynce
<pb facs="tcp:184101:14"/> and his aſſociats, yea ſo much as to gather a ſymple coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of rebellion, much leſſe of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? By whoſe autority ſhall they be declared rebelles? Shal it be by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King and Quenes autority, which haue cauſed theym to take ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their maieſties? which hath had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to them in hir dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger? whiche therein hath encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them by words &amp; letters? and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks for their ſeruice hath approued &amp; accepted that whiche they haue done, as a meane of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeruation of this whole realme? Furthermore, there is none but knoweth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ennemies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Prince abuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the King and Queene, whoſe wyll they keepe forced and ſubiecte to theyre wylles. Whyche ys
<pb facs="tcp:184101:14"/> the cauſe why the ſayd Prince and his aſſociates haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted hitherto, and nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne proteſt, neyther to hold nor acknowledge any Edict, ſtatute or ordinaunce, made vnder the name of the Kyng, whileſte hys libertye is taken from him by the vyolence and armes of their enemies.</p>
            <p>And for that they take for proofe, beſides theſe thynges heretofore writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whych ſo oft y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Queene hath ſente them word of: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is that ſhe could not agre to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary part was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtronger, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And although y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſince the moneth of Aprill the Kynges Maieſty hath ben forced, and they haue bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to abuſe his name &amp; autority, yet ſince that
<pb facs="tcp:184101:15"/> tyme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing hath been more clerely knowen and manifeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in a letter of the Queenes to <hi>Monſiur de Vieillevile</hi> and the Countye of <hi>Villars,</hi> dated the 14. of Maye laſte. Where ſhe wryte with her hand, that ſhe committed the kyng her ſonn into the handes of the other: meaning by the other, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the ſaid Lord Prince. Wherby it appeareth that the iudgement of rebellion and al other things made vnder the name and authority of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king againſt the ſayd Prynce and hys company, ought to be eſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med to be made by their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: ſeeyng that the kyng is vnder their handes, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth euen by the witneſſe of the Queene.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:15"/>
            <p>Now then I leaue to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, of what weighte that iudgement of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, which is geuen by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parties &amp; enemies of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned? but yet let vs ſee what that great cryme is which they cal rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, &amp; wherupon they grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that, which they lay to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde Princes charge and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany? It is (ſay they) bicauſe they wyll not geue ouer theyr armour. If it be ſo, I demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what ſhal they be caled, which comming to the courte in armoure, though they had none enemies armed againſt them, wold not neuertheleſſe geue ouer their armoure, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they receiued co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente from the kynge, and which yet hold them with the ſame boldneſſe that they toke
<pb facs="tcp:184101:16"/> them at the beginning. Now who is he that would gyue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his armour at the requeſt &amp; inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of hys enemy, which hath the ſworde ready in hys hand to fight wyth him? what other thing is it, to demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaid Prince ſhuld diſarme himſelf his aduerſaries remai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning armed, but only to wyll that his enemies ſhuld be hys maſters, that hys goods ſhuld be ſubiecte to their greedye couetouſneſſe, that hys lyfe ſhould be giuen ouer to their cruelty? To be ſhort, that he ſhuld receiue the law of thoſe, which hauing none, ought to receiue theſame of others?</p>
            <p>And furthermore is it not to breake the wall which it hath pleaſed God to ſet aboute hys poore Church of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes to gyue it ouer to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:184101:16"/> rage &amp; fury of thoſe, which can not be ſatiſfied wyth ſuckyng of Innocentes bloud.</p>
            <p>Furthermore it is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayd Prince hath always offred to vnarme hym ſelf, if hys enemies would vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arme them firſt, &amp; wythdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Kyng, would leaue him in his fyrſt li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berty. Now is it not reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which firſt toke armor w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, &amp; agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kinges wil, againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Edicts, agaynſt the expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: ſhuld lay down their armour, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other which were ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med after the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: armed (I ſay) by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, authority &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king &amp; Quene, for the conſeruation of their Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyes and of theyre Edictes,
<pb facs="tcp:184101:17"/> againſt the oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the other?</p>
            <p>To be ſhort let al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayd Prynce hath done be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and it ſhalbe founde that hys anſweres, and proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hys offers, &amp; all hys doin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, are ſufficiente witneſſes, of hys innocency. For hath he not gone about by al meanes to ſet this realme at quiet? &amp; to deliuer it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perill which ſemeth to threaten it with an extreme and vtter ruine?</p>
            <p>What co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of peace being any thyng reaſonable was euer refuſed, or not rather ſought by the ſaid Prince and hys company? How oft hath he gone about to let the entry of ſtraungers into thys realme, fearing the inconueniences that myghte thereof enſue?
<pb facs="tcp:184101:17"/> Hath he not geuen to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the deſert of hys cauſe, to ſtraunge Prynces, &amp; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the confederates of this crown, beſeching the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take vp the matter, &amp; to be meane of the quietneſſe and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of this realme? With what modeſty hath he behaued him ſelfe, in the townes wherin he myght conſerue the liberty of their conſciences, and the exer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſing of their religion, folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the permiſſion and ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce of the kyng? Hath he vſed any one poynt of viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or iniuſtice? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his enemies forcing townes, &amp; not beeing content to bereue them of the benefite and liberalitie of the kyng touching religion, haue committed ſo many murthers and ſpoyles, that the ſtreates
<pb facs="tcp:184101:18"/> haue bene paued with deade corpſes, and the earth ſtained with the bloud of the Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes which they haue ſhed. Let men the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudge without affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who thei be which by their workes and effectes, haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to be declared rebelles: eyther the Prynce and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, which haue armed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to maintaine the Edic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the King, made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the aduyſe of the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes (which ought to take place during y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minority of his ſayd Maieſty) his liberty, the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes liberty, and the quietneſſe of the common welth: or their e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nemies, which taki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g armes, without authority of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King, haue broken hys Edictes, ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his townes, murdred hys ſubiects, &amp; ſet forth ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces
<pb facs="tcp:184101:18"/> quite contrary to the Kings, &amp; namly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Edict of Ianuary made ſo ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nely, as we haue ſaid, receued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole conſent throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme, &amp; lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe gretly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. If then w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eye al the partes of this cauſe bee marked, it ſhalbe found, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayd Pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany haue been falſly called rebelles by thoſe which are very rebelles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: they haue bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared ſedicious by thoſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> late King Henry, haue ben cauſe of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troubles which haue happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in thys realme: and haue ben declared gilty of treſon by thoſe, which oppreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings maieſty, aboliſh his ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces &amp; abuſe his name &amp; authory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to magnify the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to his
<pb facs="tcp:184101:19"/> ouerthrow. Thoſe, yea thoſe ar gilty of diuine treaſon, whoſe works haue alwayes ſhewed that they holde Ambicion for their God, Couetouſneſſe for their religion, &amp; the pleaſures of this worlde for their para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe &amp; greateſt felicitie: whiche haue ſworne warre againſte the ſonne of God, againſt hys worde and thoſe which main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine it: which ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes of Anabaptiſtry in baptizing againe thoſe children, whiche be already baptized according to the inſtitution &amp; ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte: which haue their houſes ful of ſpoyles, and their handes em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brued with bloudy crueltie.</p>
            <p>They alſo are giltie of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane treaſon, whiche haue broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Edictes of the kyng,
<pb facs="tcp:184101:19"/> haue approched and ſeazed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon hys perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hys commaundement, which are great frendes, and haue made thoſe to be their in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruments in thys feat, which would violently haue taken a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waye the ſeconde perſon of Fraunce, and haue oppreſſed the kyng, and brought hys eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate to confuſion and ruyne. And to ſpeake further, I ſaye that they are giltie of treaſon, whiche made of late y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> curſed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracy in Prouince, by the handes of <hi>Lauris</hi> preſidente in the court of parlemente at <hi>Aix,</hi> and conioyned with <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brice Cerbelome</hi> Gouernoure of Auignon for the Pope, which tended to aſſemble xv. M. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſhould marche (as they were ſworen, at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb facs="tcp:184101:20"/> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Guiſe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of the ſayd <hi>Fabritius</hi> furniſhed a thouſand footemen, and .CC. horſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which conſpiracy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come to knowlege, &amp; very<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the court of parlament of Prouince, <hi>Entrages, &amp; Laidet,</hi> two pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipal captaines of this factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wer behedded by iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment giuen in the ſame court. And if thys ſuffyce not, I will adde more: that the ſayd Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes haue made the lyke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy in <hi>Dauphine,</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> captaine <hi>Mantill:</hi> hoping by this meane to make <hi>Dauphine</hi> to take ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes with <hi>Prouince</hi> to martche together at their pleaſure. In ſo much that theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracies made to aboliſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preaching of the Goſpell, theſe takings vp of men, theſe othes taking to martch at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maudeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of
<pb facs="tcp:184101:20"/> the Guyſe, cry out, that as wel the ſayd Guyſe as his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours are rebelles, and gilty of treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both to God and man. And contrarywiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe are true &amp; faythfull ſeruantes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King, which haue withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; ſtoutly do withſtande theyr rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſeditions &amp; atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts, againſt the Kinges Maieſtie and eſtate of all thys realme. And beſydes this that I haue ſpoken, let the ouerwhelming of the gouernment &amp; iuſtice of this realme be witneſſe, and namely that courte of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Paris:</hi> which thei haue made theyr inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in thys falſe &amp; pernitious iudgement of rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: bicauſe they could not finde any other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany ſo corrupt &amp; depraued, ſo bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; ſlaue to their wils &amp; appetites as that.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:21"/>
            <p>As in effecte all thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne there at thys daye, doe eyther holde theyr eſtates through the fauor of the ſayd Guyſes and their adherentes, or els hope to haue ſome other by their meane. And euen the principal amongeſt them are plainly compryſed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy and faction made by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Guyſe and hys adheren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: wherof we at this day fele the lamentable and miſerable effectes. And we muſt in dede truly confeſſe, that amongeſt al the plagues that God long hath ſcourged thys poore and afflicted realme withall, thys ought to be accompted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt: that ſuch a court of parle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whiche oughte to be the ſeate of Iuſtice, the refuge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oppreſſed, the brydle and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:184101:21"/> of al vice, ſhuld be ſo farre from hys ryght and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall vſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhould open the gate to al iniuſtice and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, to al impunitie and lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of euil doing. Wherby is come to paſſe, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principal head of the gouernement of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce being ſo ſicke, hath ſpread her diſeaſe vpon al the parts and members of thys kyngdome. And for profe herof, marke not only the particular wronges done by the ſayd court to infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cryes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plaints, the bloud of ſo many poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents as it hath oppreſſed, condemned, and murthered.</p>
            <p>But principally marke thys falſe and peruerſe iudgement of rebellion, which is a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wrong done to infinite perſons, whoſe lyfe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation
<pb facs="tcp:184101:22"/> hath made proofe of the moſte humble obedience which they beare to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges maieſty. Now to the end that theſe corrupt iudges ſhoulde leaue behynde no one poynte of iniuſtice, they haue pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced thys iudgement, the cauſe not being heard, the reaſons not debated, the proues of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying and innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande. And although they were refuſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Prince and hys company (which was duely notified vnto them) they neuertheleſſe left not to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of thys fact, to geue al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeates of the courte of parlemente of <hi>Paris,</hi> there are now none other iudges, but corruptions, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treds, and priuate affections,
<pb facs="tcp:184101:22"/> and there is now none other law but contemning and abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhing of the kynges lawes &amp; cuſtomes of thys realme.</p>
            <p>Wherupon my maſters, you which are called Iudges, I demaund what iniuſtice and manifeſt corruption is, if thys whych you haue done in thys iudgement be not? For where is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of iuſtice obſerued? Where are the reaſons wyth which the condemned haue bene ouercome? Where is that auncient and righteous law, that ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not both be iudges and particular enemies? Why haue you thruſt your ſelues in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thoſe, which haue refuſed you for iudges, hauing as much reaſon to do it, as there are faultes of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraunte wronges in you?
<pb facs="tcp:184101:23"/> And to be ſhort were you not ryghtly refuſed, which haue driuen out of your companye, al thoſe which you perceaued not to be of your faction? You which by the decree the laſt of Iune now paſſed, put weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the hande of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, againſt both GOD and mannes lawes, yea againſte your own lawes, againſte the common wealth and vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal quietneſſe of thys realme? You which haue proclamed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynyſters of the reformed Churches giltie of treaſon, whom neuertheleſſe the kyng by hys proclamation hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued to hys protection, and who for thys effect haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the othe at your handes? You which durſt declare to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng yea wyth threatninges, by
<pb facs="tcp:184101:23"/> 
               <hi>Monſieur Chambon and Monſieur Fay</hi> youre deputyes, that ye thought ſtraunge and would not ſuffer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> agreement which he would haue made betwene the ſayd Prynce and hys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries? By thys meane ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng away all doubt, that ye are the ſworen enemies of the ſayd Prynce and hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, and conſequently ſhuttyng your owne mouthes, that ye might not pronounce any ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſt them? And what nedeth any more? Loke vppon the head citie of this realme, where your abiding is, and marke the extreame cruelties which are dayly committed by the people, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> before youre eyes, to your knowlege, wyll, &amp; prouoking. Let men conſider the refuſe that you made to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:184101:24"/> Lord of <hi>Briſſac,</hi> to make any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donaunce to repreſſe theſe tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multes of the people. Let it be weyghed as appertayneth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt part of you, the better to ſhew that they wyl no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger vſe iuſtice, but force, ar of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidentes &amp; counſelers become menne of warre: haue chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their pennes into ſwords, and their longe gounes into corcelets, they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues play the captaines, &amp; go publique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly armed, with other ſuch inſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lenties, as vnworthy of their eſtate, as very mete to the cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruption of their lyfe. Let all theſe thynges (I ſay) be conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered, and if it be ſo that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles can not iudge of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troublers of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quietneſſe can not knowe of ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the breakers
<pb facs="tcp:184101:24"/> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kynges Edictes, are not able to iudge of giltineſſe of treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: if ſo be (I ſay) that thoſe which deſerue to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, ought not to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne others: Ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not deny but they which ye haue conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reaſon, not only to refuſe you, but alſo to cauſe you to be punyſhed in tyme &amp; place, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſert of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice. Which thyng the moſt part of thys realme greatly de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſireth, beyng aſſured that god wyll ſhewe vs hys mercyfull face, when he rayſeth vp in Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce good &amp; faithful iudges which ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne &amp; rightly puniſhe thoſe, which vniuſtly haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned other: executi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vpon your perſons, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence whiche you haue pronounced agaynſt the innocentes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:25"/>
            <p>All theſe thinges tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyng equally weyghed, ſhal plainly ſhew, to al thoſe which in this cauſe ſhal geue iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t free from all particular affection, that although there bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſet forth for the defence of the ſayd Prynce and hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany, againſt the intollerable iniuſtice, &amp; the vnworthyneſſe which hath ben ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by thys iudgement, yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe their innocency is ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraunt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is able to ſpeake it ſelfe, and beelye the falſe &amp; ſhameleſſe ſlaunders, of their ennemie iudges.</p>
            <p>Now I leaue to thynk, how iuſt grief it is to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Prince whan he hath faythfully obey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed all thynges whych wer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded hym, for the tuition of the Kyng and Queene, and
<pb facs="tcp:184101:25"/> whan he had done the duetye of that place which he holdeth in thys realme, as behoued a moſt faythfull and louing ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt of the Kyng, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the wealth and profit of al thys realme: that hys de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert ſhould be payde wyth ſo great vnthankfulneſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the duety whych he hath ſhewed to the Kyng ſhould be turned to cryme, and that hys obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhould be called rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thys certainly is with good right not only greuous vnto hym, but alſo intollerable.</p>
            <p>And although this vile ſpot wherewith they woulde haue burdened hym, can not in any wyſe faſten vppon hym, but returneth to thoſe whyche brought it, neuertheleſſe he fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth hymſelf ſo bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in duty,
<pb facs="tcp:184101:26"/> not only to hys honor, but to hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is reſolued to beſtow all the meanes which God hath put and hereafter ſhal put in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, to cauſe the innocency of them al, to be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only to the people of Fraunce, but to ſtraunge nations: and to leaue the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory to our poſterity. And for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſmuch as by the wycked and corrupt iudgement, geuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt hym and thoſe of hys company, and by the maner that they haue vſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde iudgement, and namely the ouerwhelming of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtice of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce done by his enemies, he wel ynough knoweth, that the way of iuſtice beyng ſhutt vp from him, he can not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by cauſe the edictes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kyng to be obſerued, &amp; conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly
<pb facs="tcp:184101:26"/> ſhewe foorth hys innocencie: for thys cauſe he is conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to haue recourſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte remedy, of armes. Which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng in hys hande at the Queenes commaundement, and lykewyſe for hys own of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and duty (conſidering the place which he holdeth in this realme) he wil neuer leaue of, tyll he hath made the Kyng peaſibly to be obeyed in hys cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, hys edictes obſerued, and the innocency of the ſayd Prynce, and hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtli acknowleged. And the ſayd Prince declareth that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they (whoſe authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and commaundemente hath cauſed him to begin this enterpryſe,) ſhoulde nowe come and allege their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye aduyſe and opynion,
<pb facs="tcp:184101:27"/> yet though they chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge their willes, he can not chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his: as alſo he can not ſlacken his duty towardes the Kyng, nor forget the place which he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in thys realme.</p>
            <p>Therfore the ſayd Prynce &amp; all hys company proteſte, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the maieſtie of God and the Kyng, and before all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and nations to whom the knowlege of thys facte hath come or ſhal come, that they confeſſe and acknowlege the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues moſt humble and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſubiectes and ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kyng their ſoueraine Lord and Prynce. and that their armes are not, nor neuer ſhalbe againſt hys maieſtye, but agaynſte hys enemyes. Whom they hold for rebelles, ſetiouſe, and giltye of treaſon
<pb facs="tcp:184101:27"/> to God and man: bicauſe they haue ouerthrowen the lawes and cuſtomes of thys realme, haue broken the Edictes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kyng, and violate the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtates, in thruſting themſelues into the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of hys maieſtie, (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche they were excluded by the aduiſe of the ſaid eſtates) and haue dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out the faythfull and law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full counſelers of the Kyng. Furthermore bicauſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende themſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, enforce hys liberty, abuſe hys name, to coloure their am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and inſaciable crueltie, they haue made and dayly do make conſpiracies, factions, and practiſes as wel to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne their vſurpation, as to vndoo the moſte parte of the Kynges faythfull ſubiectes.
<pb facs="tcp:184101:28"/> And namely to banyſh out of Fraunce the pure preaching of the Goſpell, to ſpoyle &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thoſe which make profeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion therof. Agaynſt thoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onely, &amp; for theſe cauſes, with the other that depend on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſayd Prynce &amp; hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany proteſt to haue weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for great nede, hauing none other meane to kepe the Kynges maieſtie, hys edictes, hys hyghneſſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtate of hys croune, the authoritie of hys eſtates, the lyfe and goods of an infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of his poore ſubiectes, and principally the pure ſeruice of god eſtabliſhed in thys realme by the authori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of the Kyng. The impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce of which thinges doth ſo touche the ſayde Prynces heart and hys company, that
<pb facs="tcp:184101:28"/> foreſeing the horrible calami<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie and deſolation that myght happen to thys realme, &amp; that all Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhuld bathe in hys own bloud, if their ennemies myght continue the murthers and cruelties which thei haue exerciſed theſe .v. monethes, they all determine to let for no payne, to eſtabliſhe the quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thys realme, but to ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter their lyues, to aſſure the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of ſo many good, &amp; fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubiectes and ſeruauntes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng. And are not hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but rather encouraged by that pernicious iudgement of rebellion: the which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt not to hold as iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but ſlaunder practyzed and ſette foorth by theyr enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes. So that withſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:184101:29"/> it, they meane not to w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtande the wyll of the Kyng, or any iudgement geuen forth by a court of parliamente lawfully aſſembled: but a viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, force, oppreſſion and inuading of their goods and lyues, by the Kynges enemies and theirs. The ſayd Prince deſireth not onely all thoſe of thys realme whiche oughte to eſteme the Kynges ſeruice, but alſo all ſtraunge Prynces which loue equitie and iuſtice, to w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtande with hym ſo violent oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made to a yong Kyng: whoſe great vertues already ſhini<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in hym, geue certayne hope, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beyng come to age, he wyl ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlege the ſeruice and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour whych hath ben done to hym, in hys great and vrgent neceſſitie. And namely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:184101:29"/> Prynce deſireth al ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, as well Almaines as Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, that are come into thys realme, and do ayde hys ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, that they remember the title of equitie, the memory wherof hath at all tymes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored their aunceters: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wyll not ſuffer ſuche reproche to lyght on them, as that they haue fought for an euil cauſe, againſt a good cauſe: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes of the kyng, agaynſte hys faythfull ſubiectes: for Prynces y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be but ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, agaynſt a Prince of the bloud of thys croune: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauourers of the Pope and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Churche of Rome, againſte thoſe whyche profeſſe the Goſpel of our lord Ieſus Chriſt. And herein the ſayd Prince, caleth before the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeate of god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciences
<pb facs="tcp:184101:30"/> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſtraungers, which profeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, to tak hede that they be not cauſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid goſpel be baniſhed out of thys poore kyngdome, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all they which profeſſe theſame, be ſpoyled &amp; murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. He praieth them alſo to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys ennemies whatſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer they ſpeake of rebellion, aſſayle hym neuertheleſſe for none other cauſe, but for that folowing the edict of the king, he mayntayneth the pure pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching of the worde of god. So the ſayd ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers oughte to preuente, (that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ennemies of their religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Princes and hys companies) ſhoulde think in mockage (as they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready do) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue begiled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; haue brought to paſſe bi their practiſes, that their own
<pb facs="tcp:184101:30"/> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which maintaine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell, are come to fyghte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them in Fraunce. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Prynce prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to conſider what wil folowe of thys matter: leaſte if the ennemies ouercome the goſpellers in this realme, that their enterpriſe ſhould ſtretch out beyond y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ryne, &amp; ſo they themſelues may be aſſailed in their houſes, according to the confederacy which they haue made wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope &amp; diuerſe other ſtraunge Prynces. And though hitherto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Prince hathe deferred to call anye ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges to the ſuccour of the kyng, &amp; of them which it hath pleaſed hym to permyt to liue according to the reformation of the goſpel, neuertheleſſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys ennemies haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon
<pb facs="tcp:184101:31"/> to cal them in their euill cauſe, he proteſteth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> herafter he wyll not let to vſe their aid for the maintenaunce of hys ryght. And ſo much the rather bicauſe he is aſſured, that the conſeruation of the kyng and of this realme, is ioined w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the conſeruation of hys innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy.</p>
            <p>Wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foraſmuchas ſuch warre, which kyndleth day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more and more, can not but bryng great calamities w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it, the ſayd Prynce &amp; hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany proteſt before God &amp; man not to be giltie therein, but they which haue been the mouers and authors therof. To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blame of al the euels &amp; inconuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of thys preſent warr, may redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ennemies which are the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and cauſe therof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:31"/>
            <p>Finally the ſayd Prynce wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and deſireth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proteſtation may ſerue alſo to confirme the aſſociatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is betwene hym and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces Lordes, gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and other, which folow hym, and ſhall hereafter follow. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayd Prynce promyſeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as he hath thys honor to be their head, and ſeyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med Churches of thys realme haue throwen themſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hys armes to conſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges edicte, againſt their aduerſaries and enemies of this croune: he wil be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal geue hys lyfe &amp; his goods, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſeruice of god may be eſtabliſhed in hys pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, thoſe whiche profeſſe it maintained, the kyng ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne at hys full libertie, hys
<pb facs="tcp:184101:32"/> ennemies driuen away, &amp; hys counſell reſtored according to the lawes &amp; cuſtomes of thys realme: &amp; namely the laſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſte of the eſtates.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Prynce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth &amp; prayeth al hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny to march wyth him fote by fote in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo good &amp; holy an enterpryſe, hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteouſneſſe of the cauſe, &amp; putting al their force in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength of god: ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> being certaine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fighting for the ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauncement of hys glory, the releuing of hys Churches, the conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their king, and the quietnes of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey; they ſhal fele the aſſiſtaunce &amp; ſuccour of God. Whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Prynce and hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany moſt hartily beſecheth to take in hande y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defence of their cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:184101:32"/> and for thys effecte to ſit in throne of hys iuſtice, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they preſent the horry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blaſphemies ſpued out by their ennemies againſte hys maieſtie, the crueltie whiche they vſe againſt his Churchs, the bloud of ſo many innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which they haue ſpilt, &amp; their bloudy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracies and da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enterpryſes, agaynſte hys glory and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe of hys childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſeruauntes. So that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing into hys protection hys poore people and thoſe whyche mayntayne them, he maye place hys power, iuſtice, and wyſdome, againſte the boldneſſe, iniquitie, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll deuiſes of ſuche as aſſaile them, and that ſo by the dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce of hys, he make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſte to all the worlde, that
<pb facs="tcp:184101:33"/> he is the ſuccoure of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, the preſeruer of hys Churche, and the iudge of hys ennemies.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Geuen at Orleance <date>the 8. of Auguſt. Anno. 1562.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Levves of Bourbon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:33"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:34"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:35"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184101:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
